rnib.org.uk 2019-11-30

# Privacy policy - RNIB - See differently

## At RNIB we are committed to protecting your privacy online. We protect any personal information you give us while you use our websites. 

This policy is written in accordance with current data protection legislation and the Privacy and Electronic Communications Regulation (PECR). If you have any questions about it, please contact our Data Protection Compliance Officer using the following details:

  *  **Email:**  [[email protected]](https://web.archive.org/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#7713160316070518031214031e18191811111e1412053705191e155918051059021c)

  *  **Address:**  Data Protection Officer, Royal National Institute of Blind People, 105 Judd Street, London WC1H 9NE

  *  **Phone:**  020 7388 1266

  *  **Fax:**  020 7388 2034

By continuing to use this website you are signifying your agreement to the terms of this privacy policy.

### Personal information

Personal information is information that can be used to identify you. It can include your name, date of birth, email address, postal address, telephone number, fax number and credit/debit card details. 

  * Read our Low Vision Privacy Policy

  * Read our ECLO Privacy Policy

#### Where we get it from

  *  **You, directly:** We collect personal information when you ask about our activities, register with us (for example registering with the online shop or to join the Connect Community), order products and services (such as publications and email newsletters), make a donation to us or otherwise give us personal information.

  *  **You, indirectly:** If you have given a third party such as a donation or campaigning platform permission to pass your information on to us

  *  **Others:** From time to time we may pay for the contact details of people who might be interested in hearing from us in future. These may come from retailers or from companies who conduct telephone surveys or social media engagement, to promote and gather support for organisations. Before we purchase contact information, we always check the wording used when your information was originally collected, to make sure that we only contact people who have actively expressed interest in receiving information from third parties.

### How do we use your information?

We use your personal information to give you the information, services or products you ask for. We can also use your information for administrative purposes, to let you know about changes and, if you agree, as part of our fundraising activities.

We sometimes also share your information with our service providers, trading companies, and associated organisations who work with us or on our behalf to help deliver the information and services you request. We take the security of your personal information seriously, and will only share it with trusted partners. The trusted partners we use for social media/digital advertising are Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, YouTube and Spotify.

RNIB is responsible for collecting your personal information. Your personal information is not shared with third parties or used in any other way (other than described in this policy or as required by law) unless you agree. 

Where indicated - usually by a tick box asking for your permission - we use your personal information to create a profile of your interests and preferences. This information is not shared with other organisations, other than those who work with us, or on our behalf, to deliver our services.

We reserve the right to share your personal information if we are legally obliged to and to enable us to apply our terms and conditions and other agreements. This includes exchanging information with other organisations for fraud and credit risk reduction.

Unfortunately, no data transmission over the Internet is 100 per cent secure. As a result, while we try to protect your personal information, RNIB cannot guarantee the security of any information you transmit to us and you do so at your own risk. When we collect your personal information we use strict procedures and security features to prevent unauthorised access.

#### What we do with your information if you are a supporter

##### Say thank you and ask for your support

We want to make sure you know that we are grateful for your support, so we will send you a “thank you” message in response to your donation. To help you understand how your donation will be spent, we will also include some information about the impact of our work and how your contribution helps us support people affected by sight loss. From time to time we will ask for further donations or support to help our work making everyday better for people with sight loss.

##### Claim Gift Aid

Gift Aid is a UK Government scheme that allows charities to reclaim the basic rate tax back from HM Revenues and Customs on donations you make. Once you have indicated to us that you’re happy for us to claim Gift Aid on your behalf and that you pay sufficient Income Tax and/or Capital Gains Tax in that particular financial year, we’ll reclaim this money at no extra cost to you thereby increasing the value of your donation. More information is available on [the GOV.UK website](https://www.gov.uk/donating-to-charity/gift-aid). RNIB will not swap or sell your data with any third parties.

##### Make the most of our fundraising and engagement activities

We have a duty to make sure that we’re spending your donations wisely, and that means doing some research and analysis to inform our decisions. We want to send the most effective messages that we can in the most efficient way possible, so in order to work out who to contact, what to say and when to get in touch, we carry out the following activities:

  *  **Segmentation:**  This is where we analyse information such as postcodes of donors, age of supporters and whether donations have been given regularly. This helps us to provide people with the most relevant information in order to identify additional opportunities for them to get involved.

  *  **Prospect profiling:**  We occasionally engage agencies to help us identify people among our supporters who are able to support at a higher level, using publicly available records such as the electoral roll, land records, ‘rich lists’, Who’s Who publications and Companies House records. We use this information to invite potential supporters to events which may be of interest to them and recruit celebrity ambassadors.

  *  **Re-targeting:** When you agree to RNIB contacting you via email, phone or post, we may use this information to show you specific advertising on social media sites that you may visit. For example, if you receive any of our fundraising information by email, we may use information such as your email address to show you carefully selected adverts from RNIB on social media websites such as Facebook, that relate to our fundraising appeals.

The databases that we keep our supporter information on are held securely within our IT network and are not sold to or traded with other organisations, whether charities or commercial businesses.

### Accessing your personal information held by RNIB

You can ask us at any time to provide you with a copy of the information we hold about you, including where and how we obtained it, why we are keeping it and what we are using it for. This is called a “subject access request” and you can make one by contacting the Data Protection Officer using the following details:

  *  **Email:**  [[email protected]](https://web.archive.org/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#b4d0d5c0d5c4c6dbc0d1d7c0dddbdadbd2d2ddd7d1c6f4c6daddd69adbc6d39ac1df)

  *  **Address:**  Data Protection Officer, Royal National Institute of Blind People, 105 Judd Street, London WC1H 9NE

  *  **Phone:**  020 7388 1266

  *  **Fax:**  020 7388 2034

We may need to ask you to provide copies of identity documents to make sure that we are releasing your information to the right person.

### Updating your personal information

Please keep your information up to date by letting us know of any changes:

  *  **Email:**  [[email protected]](https://web.archive.org/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#d8b0bdb4a8b4b1b6bd98aab6b1baf6b7aabff6adb3)

  *  **Phone:**  0303 123 9999

  *  **Address:**  Royal National Institute of Blind People, 105 Judd Street, London WC1H 9NE

### If you no longer want to hear from us

If you decide you no longer want to hear about our news, products, services, campaigning, volunteering, or fundraising activities, you can ask us to stop contacting you by emailing [[email protected]](https://web.archive.org/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#39515c55495550575c794b57505b17564b5e174c52), calling 0303 123 9999 or writing to us at Royal National Institute of Blind People, 105 Judd Street, London WC1H 9NE. You can also unsubscribe from RNIB enewsletters at any time. Just click on the "Unsubscribe" link in any of the email newsletters you receive. It appears on every enewsletter we send out and is located right at the bottom. If you are receiving care or support services from us or you use our online shop, we may still need to get in touch for administrative reasons about the services or products we provide to you. If you don't want us to contact you anymore by SMS you can email us at [[email protected]](https://web.archive.org/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#1472617a7066757d677d7a7354667a7d763a7b66733a617f), call us on 0303 123 9999  (Monday to Friday, 9am to 5pm) or write to Fundraising, RNIB, 105 Judd Street, London, WC1H 9NE.

We may not be able to completely delete all of your information from our systems, as there are some records we must keep for legal and regulatory requirements. These include Gift Aid records, sales records, case files from our care and support services, “do not call” lists and complaint files. If you would like to know more about how and why we keep your information, you can ask us for more details by contacting the Data Protection Officer using the addresses provided above.

We are also required to make sure our records are as accurate and up to date as possible. To do this, before we contact supporters we may check the contact information we have against third party databases to make sure it is still correct. We do this to ensure the accuracy of data that we already hold, and will add a new telephone number to your record if your number needs updating and we have the correct permission to call you.

If you have a comment, concern or complaint about the way your personal information has been used, please let us know so that we can make things right.

### Cookies

Cookies are small data files that are sent from a website to your computer or mobile phone. They are stored on the hard drive of your device. Some are stored just for the duration of your visit to the website, others are stored for much longer periods. By using RNIB's websites, you consent to our use of cookies. If you'd like to learn more about cookies in general, we recommend [the About Cookies website](http://www.aboutcookies.org/).

  *  **How we use cookies:** We use cookies to make our website work better for you. No official RNIB website uses cookies that give us access to any personal information about you. RNIB also uses cookies to improve the personalised advertising which is shared with you on social media. This means that we are bringing you the content which matches your interests and helps us ensure we are using our charitable funds in the most cost-efficient way. For example, we may use data based on your past behavior, such as visits to specific web pages, to show you advertising about events and support that may relate to pages you have previously visited. These cookies cannot be used to identify individuals or their personal contact information.

  *  **Profile management:** Some RNIB websites allow you to login to an account. Some of these sites use a cookie in order to remember account information, like your password. This can be helpful, meaning you don't have to remember your password each time. These cookies don't give us access to your account or your personal details.

  *  **Usability and accessibility settings:** Some RNIB websites allow you to resize text. If you use the resizing options, these settings are stored in a cookie so that your chosen text size follows you around the website. These cookies don't give us access to your personal information.

  *  **Third-party cookies:** Third-party cookies are ones that are not set directly by RNIB, but they may be dropped onto your computer by a third party when you use one of our websites, or do certain things on one of our websites. For instance we use Google Analytics and E-tracker to help us improve the website. These analytics tools use cookies that are not controlled by RNIB but which are active when you use many of our websites. Also, some RNIB websites have "Share" buttons that let you share pages with your friends through websites like Twitter and Facebook. These sites may set a cookie when you login to share things. As third party cookies aren't set by us, we can't control how they work - but we can control which websites we choose to work with. We take your privacy seriously and we would never work with a website we don't trust.

  *  **Analytics:** We want our website to be as user friendly as possible. To help us understand how well the website is working (and how we can improve it!) we use third-party analytics tools such as Google Analytics and E-tracker. Analytics tools help us collect information about how people in general use our websites. For instance, it helps us monitor how many people visit each page, how long people stay on each page, which search engines people use to find our website and which links are clicked on. These cookies do not collect or store personal information about you. Analytics data cannot be used to identify you, or to tell us what you did on our website. It is completely anonymous.

  *  **Cookies -  your choice:** Our websites work better with cookies enabled. Our cookies don't give us or anyone else access to your personal data. We strongly advise you to keep cookies enabled when you use RNIB's websites. However, you can use your browser to delete and reject cookies. There are instructions on [how to delete cookie](http://www.aboutcookies.org/how-to-delete-cookies/)s and [how to control cookies](http://www.aboutcookies.org/how-to-control-cookies/) on the 'About Cookies' website.

### Privacy and comments on our blogs

The posting of personal information in a blog comment means your information is publicly accessible. Such information can be viewed online and collected by third parties. We are not responsible for the use of information by such third parties. We strongly recommend you avoid sharing any personal information that can be used to identify you (such as your name, age, address, name of employer).

### Privacy Policy and RNIB’s gaming subsidiaries

Our subsidiary companies which raise funds from RNIB’s gaming activities will also process your information in accordance with this privacy policy. These subsidiaries are:

  * RNIB Direct Services Lottery Limited

  * RNIB Feel Good Friday Lottery Limited

More information on the [RNIB Feel Good Friday Lottery](https://lottery.rnib.org.uk/).

### Changes to this policy

We may change our privacy policy from time to time, so please check back periodically.

## Donate now

Right now we can only reach one in three of the people who need our help most. Please make a donation and help us support more blind and partially sighted people.
